Chapter 112. The blacksmith.
availing himself of the mild summer cool weather that now rained in these
latitudes, and in preparation for the peculiarly active pursuit shortly to be
anticipated, Perth, the begimed, blistered old blacksmith, had not
removed his portable forge to the hold again after concluding his contributo
work for Ahab's leg, but still retained it on deck, fast lashed to ringbolts by
the formast, being now almost incessantly invoked by the headsman and
harp puners and bowsman to do some little job for them, altering or
repairing or new shaping their various weapons and boat furniture. Often he
would be surrounded by an eager circle, all waiting to be served, holding boat
spades, pike heads, harpoons, and lances, and jealously watching his every
movement as he toiled.
Nevertheless, this old man's was a patient hammer wielded by a patient arm.
No murmur, no impatience, no petulence did come from him. Silent, slow, and
solemn, bowing over still further his chronically broken back, he toiled away,
as if toil were life itself, and the heavy beating of his hammer, the heavy
beating of his heart. And so it was, most miserable.
A peculiar walk in this old man, a certain slight but painful appearing
yawing in his gate, had at an early period of the voyage excited the
curiosity of the mariners, and to the importunity of their persisted
questionings he had finally given in. So it came to pass that everyone now knew
the shameful story of his wretched fate.
Belated and not innocently one bitter winter's midnight on the road running
between two country towns, the blacksmith half stupidly felt the deadly
numbness stealing over him, and sought refuge in a leaning, dilapidated barn.
The issue was the loss of the extremities of both feet. Out of this
revelation, part by part, at last came out the four acts of the gladness and
the one long and as yet uncatastrophied fifth act of the grief of his life's drama.
He was an old man who at the age of nearly 60 had postponedly encountered
that thing in sorrows technicals called ruin. He had been an artisan of famed
excellence and with plenty to do, owned a house and garden, embraced a youthful
daughter-like loving wife and three bllythe ruddy children. Every Sunday
went to a cheerful looking church planted in a grove. But one night under
cover of darkness, and further concealed in a most cunning disguisement, a
desperate burglar slid into his happy home and robbed them all of everything.
and darker yet to tell, the blacksmith himself did ignorantly conduct this
burglar into his family's heart. It was the bottle conjurer. Upon the opening of
that fatal cork, fourth flew the fiend, and shriveled up his home. Now, for
prudent, most wise, and economic reasons, the blacksmith's shop was in
the basement of his dwelling, but with a separate entrance to it, so that always
had the young and loving healthy wife listened with no unhappy nervousness,
but with vigorous pleasure to the stout ringing of her young armed old husband's
hammer, whose reverberations, muffled by passing through the floors and walls,
came up to her not unsweetly in her nursery. And so to stout labor's iron
lulli, the blacksmith's infants were rocked to slumber. Oh, woe on woe, oh
death, why cast thou not sometimes be timely? Hast thou taken this old
blacksmith to thyself heir his full ruin came upon him? Then had the young widow
had a delicious grief, and her orphans a truly venerable, legendary sire to dream
of in their after years, and all of them a careing competency. But death plucked
down some virtuous elder brother on whose whistling daily toil solely hung
the responsibilities of some other family, and left the worse than useless
old man standing, till the hideous rot of life should make him easier to
harvest. Why tell the whole? The blows of the basement hammer every day grew
more and more between, and each blow every day grew fainter than the last.
The wife sat frozen at the window with tearless eyes, glitteringly gazing into
the weeping faces of her children. The bellows fell, the forge choked up with
cinders. The house was sold. The mother dived down into the long churchyard
grass. Her children twice followed her thither, and the houseless, familyless
old man staggered off a vagabond in crepe, his every woe unreverenced, his
gray head a scorn to flax and curls.
Death seems the only desirable sequel for a career like this. But death is
only a launching into the region of the strange untried. It is but the first
salutation to the possibilities of the immense remote, the wild, the watery,
the unsured. Therefore, to the death-longing eyes of such men, who
still have left in them some interior compunctions against suicide, does the
all contributed and all receptive ocean alluringly spread forth his whole plane
of unimaginable taking terrors and wonderful new life adventures. And from
the hearts of infinite Pacifics, the thousand mermaids sing to them. Come
hither, brokenhearted. Here is another life without the guilt of intermediate
death. Here are wonders supernatural without dying for them. Come hither,
bury thyself in a life which to your now equally abhored and abhoring landed
world is more oblivious than death. Come hither. Put up thy gravestone too within
the churchyard, and come hither till we marry thee.
Hearkening to these voices, east and west, by early sunrise, and by fall of
Eve, the blacksmith's soul responded, "I I come." And so Perth went away.